ILGWU. Northeast Department records 5780/050
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Northeast Department records
1933-1983
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/050
2.33 cubic feet
2.3 linear ft.
Speeches, appointment books, calendars, reports.
The first box of this collection contains the diaries (1950-1959) of David Gingold noting meetings, conferences, and important phone conversations, as well as the appointment books (1950-1970) of David Gingold scheduling trips, conferences, meetings, luncheons and holidays. The second box contains the speeches and statements (1944-1960) made by David Gingold, and publications of the Northeast Department.
5491422
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
B. Wlaker, October 28, 2008
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, June 06, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
David Gingold was born in Poland on December 10, 1896, arrived in the United States in 1912 as a teenager, and began working in the raincoat trade, joining Rainwear Local 20. He held several offices in Local 20 including a member of the executive board in 1922 and vice-chairman in 1923. In 1924, Gingold was elected manager of Local 20 and from 1925-1929 served on the ILGWU General Executive Board (GEB) and as a vice president of the union. Gingold briefly returned to shop work before becoming an organizer in 1934. After time spent organizing areas of Pennsylvania and New England, Gingold assumed the directorship of the Northeast Department in 1943, a position he held until his retirement in 1977. He was again elected a vice president and member of the ILGWU GEB in 1946. He died on December 15, 1980 at the age of 84.
Biographical / Historical
The Cotton Garment and Miscellaneous Trades Department was established in 1935, and renamed the Northeast Department In 1946. At the time of its formation, the department was responsible for Pennsylvania (outside of Philadelphia), Massachusetts (outside of Boston), New York (north of Albany), Delaware, Rhode Island, New Hampshire, Vermont, Maine, and parts of New Jersey (Harry Crone, "35 Northeast," New York: ILGWU, 1970, 18-19.).
In the 1970s, the ILGWU underwent major reorganization, resulting in changes in the Northeast Department's jurisdiction and name. With the formation of the New England Region in 1975, the Northeast Department no longer had jurisdiction in Maine, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Rhode Island, or Vermont. In 1976, responsibility for upstate New York was shifted to the newly-established New York State District. In 1977, the Eastern Pennsylvania Region organized and serviced members in the former Northeast Department areas of New Jersey and parts of Pennsylvania (Easton, Allentown, and Philadelphia). In 1979, the New Jersey Region took over the parts of New Jersey previously covered by the Northeast Department.
The Northeast Department was reorganized to be the Northeast, Western Pennsylvania and Ohio Department in 1978.
Vice President Elias Reisberg, General Manager of the Philadelphia Joint Board, served as director from 1935 until his death in 1943. David Gingold succeeded Reisberg, serving as director until his retirement in 1977. Sol Hoffman served as director of this ILGWU's Northeast, Western Pennsylvania and Ohio Department from 1977 until 1995.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of two types of records, those relating to David Gingold in his role as director of the Northeast Department and the administrative records of the department.
Included are appointment books by year for David Gingold and also Sol Chaikin, in which are marked meetings and appointments with individuals, allowing the researcher to view the daily calendars of these two individuals. Also available is the Daily Business Journal of presumably Gingold. It is arranged by day and provides an account of who he talked to, who he spoke to on the phone, who he met with, what was discussed, and what business was carried out on that particular day, providing daily accounts of Gingold and his work for the department. Additionally, there are speeches given by Gingold, typed out with handwritten notations for union events, local meetings, conferences, installation ceremonies, and dinners, such as retirement dinners for locals under his jurisdiction.
The second component of the collection focuses on the general organizational function of the department and includes reports from the Northeast Department to the GEB, handbooks, guides published by and for the Northeast Department, and minutes for various locals that were under the jurisdiction of the Northeast Department, including Local 93 Reading PA, and Local 109-131 Scranton PA.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records
Women's clothing industry -- United States.; Women's clothing industry -- New York.; Labor unions -- United States -- Clothing workers.; Labor unions -- New York -- Clothing workers.; Clothing workers -- United States.; Clothing workers -- New York.; Industrial relations -- United States.; Industrial relations -- New York.; Gingold, David.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. -- Northeast Department.
5491422
- David Gingold Speeches, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- David Gingold. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- [No Name]. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Scope and Contents
  2 copies
- S. C. Chaiken. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- David Gingold. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- S. C. Chaiken. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- David Gingold. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- S. C. Chaiken. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- David Gingold. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- [No Name]. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- S. C. Chaiken. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- David Gingold. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- [No Name]. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- [No Name]. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- S. C. Chaiken. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- S. C. Chaiken. Appointment Book and Daily Memoranda, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- [No Name]. Daily Business Journal, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- [No Name]. Daily Business Journal. (1 of 2), 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- [No Name]. Daily Business Journal. (2 of 2), 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- [No Name]. Daily Business Journal, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- David Gingold Speeches, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- David Gingold Speeches, 1946-1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- David Gingold Speeches, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- A Policy Guide on Enforcing the Union Agreement (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Undated
- Minutes. Reading Local 93, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- ILGWU. Northeast Department. Report to the General Execuritve Board, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- ILGWU Northeast Department. Guide in Setting Piece Rates in Dress Joint Council Shops, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- ILGWU. Northeast Department. Dress Guide for Piece Rates, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Minutes Book of the David Crystal Shop, 1943-1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Minutes. Finance Committee. Local 109 and 131, 1938-1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Minutes. Local 131, 1935-1940 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Your Union. Wyoming Valley District Council. Northeast Department. ILGWU (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- 28th Convention Report (Box 4, Folder 4)
- The Principles of Unionis (Questions and Answers). ILGWU Education Department, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Holiday Messages, 1960-1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Union Newsletters, 1960-1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Union Newspapers/Newsletters, 1961-1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- An Outline of Grievance Procedures in the Garment Industry. Northeast Department. ILGWU, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Staff Conference Report. Northeast Department. ILGWU, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Aug 20-Aug 22, 1967
- Pamphlet. 35th Anniversary. Tri-district Health Center, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Politics and the Garment Worker. Parts 1 and 2. Northeast Department. ILGWU (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Policy Guides on Enforcing the Union Agreement, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Dress Guide for Piece Rates. Northeast Department. ILGWU, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Notes (Box 4, Folder 16)